We are human and we make mistakes,
but it's more important to
correct them once we discover them. There are
so many options available in health insurance policies
that there's a high chance
we could buy the wrong health insurance policy.
But after buying the wrong health insurance policy, can
we
cancel it? In today's video,
friends, we'll explore the
rules, terms, and conditions for canceling a health insurance policy. Can
we cancel our health insurance policy mid-year?
If yes,
how much will be deducted from the premium we paid to
get our money back?
We'll also explain the complete step-by-step process of health insurance policy cancellation. So,
if you've made such a mistake, or there's a chance you
might, today's video will
save you a significant amount of money and effort. The
information and guidance provided in this video won't cost you a single rupee. So, do
n't delay and quickly
start the video.
We divide the cancellation into two parts according to the timing. The
first part is the free look period, that is, when we
buy our health insurance policy online or offline, then after that the insurance
companies give us an opportunity to understand this policy
and if we are
cancelling our policy within this free look period, then
we do not have to face any deduction, that is, no
money will be deducted from our paid premium,
we will get the entire amount refunded.
Now why do we want to cancel this health insurance policy?
Brother, we feel that
this policy is not right for us or it
may be that the coverage which was told to us
before buying the policy is not there in this policy. There are too
many terms and
conditions in it. There are very few cashless hospitals or
doctors which do not seem sufficient to me as per my city, for
my treatment,
this policy
is too expensive or there can be any reason, you
can cancel it if you are dissatisfied,
you will get the entire premium amount refunded,
but this free look period is for how many days,
when you do any  You purchase a health insurance
policy and
receive the policy document, whether hard
or soft.
Your free look period is 15 to 30 days after receiving the policy document.
If you purchased this health insurance
policy online from a broker or
an online website, your free look
period will be 30 days
after receiving the policy document. If you purchased this policy
offline from an agent or an
insurance company branch, your
free look period will be 15 days.
If you need to cancel the policy within this time frame,
you can do so. You wo
n't have to face any deductions. Therefore,
whenever you purchase a health insurance policy,
review and understand it thoroughly within the free look period so that if you
decide to cancel the policy, you
can do so timely and you wo
n't have to face any deductions. You get your entire money
back. The second part of the health insurance
policy cancellation timing is
your
remaining year. That is,
you can cancel your health insurance policy within the entire year, excluding the free look period.
If during this entire year, you
ever feel that there is some condition or
deficiency in this policy due to which
you do not want to continue this policy,
then you can apply for cancellation and even
after that you will get the refund amount.
We will discuss the complete process of health insurance policy cancellation
later in the video, but first let us
discuss
how much money the
insurance company will deduct from our refund amount depends on the
timing of our policy cancellation, that is, how much time out of the entire 12 months of the year,
we have
kept this policy. The insurance company will refund our premium on a pro rata basis in the same ratio by
deducting the money for the time used. Now the deduction can be different for every
insurance company and according to your premium
payment frequency, that is, the
percentage of refund on pro rata basis can be different for every insurance company and
how you pay the premium, that is, you pay the
premium on a monthly frequency or half
yearly.  Your deduction will
also fluctuate depending on whether you pay quarterly or annually.
If you want to know the exact percentage of
how much money you will get if you cancel your policy, then
check the policy word selection section of your health insurance policy, there you will
also get to know your percentage as per the timing.
In today's video, I am going to tell you the deductions
of Star Health Assure Plan as an example,
that at which time in the whole year
you will cancel, how much
money you will get, you can use these deductions as a reference.
If you apply for cancellation within one month after the free look period, then the
insurance company will
return your premium to you by deducting 22.5%. I am
talking about Star Health Assure Plan,
for a reference purpose only. If you apply for
cancellation of your policy between 1 to 3 months, then there will be a
deduction of 3.57%. 3 to 6 months
When you apply for cancellation, then
at 57.5% and if the time is between 6 to 9 months since
you have
taken the policy, then 80% of your premium will be deducted at the
time of refund and if
you apply for policy cancellation after 9 months, then
you will not get any refund amount
because you have used your policy for
most of the time. Now suppose
you have used the policy for any period of the year
and during the tenure of that policy a
claim comes and after filing the claim,
if you want to apply for policy cancellation, will the
insurance company refund your money? This will
not happen because the
first condition for cancellation of a health insurance policy is
that there should be no claim on it
because if you file a claim then
you have used the policy and
after using the policy, there is no liability of the health
insurance company to give any refund.
Now
this is pro rata deduction i.e. time based.
Deductions are deducted from your policy premium.
Apart from this, are there any other
charges that can be deducted from your refund amount? There are
some charges and
expenses that can be deducted. The
first deduction that can be made is the
cost of medical tests. If the health insurance company conducted any medical tests when you
purchased this health insurance policy
and the insurance company paid for these medical tests, then
those charges can also be deducted from your refund amount. The
second type of
expense that can be deducted is
administrative charges, i.e., the
operational cost of issuing the policy. That money can
also be deducted from your refund amount.
And the third, as I told you, is
on a pro rata basis, that is, based on the number of months
you have used the policy, the
money will be deducted in the same ratio.
Exact percentages will be credited to your policy.
Now, friends, the final question comes:
how do we apply for cancellation of our health insurance policy?
What is the complete process for it?  If we want to
know, then the first step is
that you have to get
in touch with the health insurance company. You have to
inform them through a call or email that you
want to cancel your policy.
In the second step, you will
send a return request to your health insurance company.
You can send this only through a letter, that is,
you can also send a letter physically to
their address or you can also
send this request to them through an email,
but it should be a return request.
You have to send a request in written form for
policy cancellation. In
this request, you will have to mention the details of your policy
and along with this,
you will also have to mention the exact reason for cancellation. The
third step comes friends.
When your request reaches the insurance company,
what will be their reaction? It is obvious that
their clients are angry. They are
not happy with this policy, so they will try to
resolve the reason for your cancellation and give you some solution. They will
try to resolve your complaint.
But if you still do not agree
and you are not able to get the policy back,  If you must cancel,
your policy will be processed for cancellation in the fourth step.
In the fifth step, friends, whatever refund
amount you receive, whether it's
after deductions on a pro rata basis or if
your policy is within the free look period, the
full refund amount will be credited to your account. The
final step is that the
insurance company will send you a cancellation
confirmation letter or email,
informing you that no risk is covered after this date
and that your
policy has now been cancelled.
Friends, in this way, if you have purchased the wrong health
insurance policy, you
can cancel it.
You also understand the terms and conditions, how much money you will get
back, and you also know the
complete step-by-step cancellation
process.
If you have any questions, doubts, or queries related to health insurance policy cancellation, please
use the comments section. As always, I will
definitely respond to your comments, and where necessary, I will also
Please share this information
so that any needy person can benefit from this information.
To show your love and support, you can like the video. If you
are new to the channel or you have
not subscribed to the channel, then please do subscribe to the channel.
This decision of yours will
prove to be very beneficial. I, Harvinder
Singh, now take your permission. I will take your permission
in the next video. Till then,
take care of yourself, stay happy and stay healthy. Jai
Hind.